Chapter 45.
The affidavit.
So far as what there may be of a narrative in this book, and indeed is
indirectly touching one or two very interesting and curious particulars in
the habits of sperm whales, the foregoing chapter in its earlier part is
as important to one as will be found in this volume. But the leading matter of
it requires to be still further and more familiarly enlarged upon in order to be
adequately understood, and moreover to take away any incredility which a
profound ignorance of the entire subject may induce in some minds as to the
natural verity of the main points of this affair.
I care not to perform this part of my task methodically, but shall be content
to produce the desired impression by separate citations of items practically
or reliably known to me as a whaleman, and from these citations, I take it the
conclusion aimed at will naturally follow of itself.
First, I have personally known three instances where a whale after receiving
a harpoon has affected a complete escape, and after an interval, in one
instance of 3 years, has been again struck by the same hand and slain, when
the two irons, both marked by the same private cipher, have been taken from the
body. In the instance where three years intervened between the flinging of the
two harpoons, and I think it may have been something more than that, the man
who darted them, happening in the interval to go in a trading ship on a
voyage to Africa, went ashore there, joined a discovery party, and penetrated
far into the interior, where he traveled for a period of nearly 2 years, often
endangered by serpents, savages, tigers, poisonous myasmas, with all the other
common perils incident to wandering in the heart of unknown regions. Meanwhile,
the whale he had struck must also have been on its travels. No doubt it had
thrice circumnavigated the globe, brushing with its flanks all the coasts
of Africa, but to no purpose. This man and this whale again came together, and
the one vanquished the other. I say I myself have known three instances
similar to this. That is, in two of them I saw the whales struck, and upon the
second attack saw the two irons with the respective marks cut in them afterwards
taken from the dead fish. In the three-year instance, it so fell out that
I was in the boat both times, first and last, and the last time distinctly
recognized a peculiar sort of huge mole under the whale's eye, which I had
observed there 3 years previous. I say 3 years, but I am pretty sure it was more
than that. Here are three instances then which I personally know the truth of,
but I have heard of many other instances from persons whose veracity in the
matter there is no good ground to impeach.
Secondly, it is well known in the sperm whale fishery, however ignorant the
world ashore may be of it, that there have been several memorable historical
instances where a particular whale in the ocean has been at distant times and
places popularly cognisable. Why such a whale became thus marked was not
altogether and originally owing to his bodily peculiarities as distinguished
from other whales. For however peculiar in that respect any chance whale may be,
they soon put an end to his peculiarities by killing him and boiling
him down into a peculiarly valuable oil.
No, the reason was this, that from the fatal experiences of the fishery, there
hung a terrible prestige of perilousness about such a whale, as there did about
Ronaldo Raldini, in so much that most fishermen were content to recognize him
by merely touching their tarpolins when he would be discovered, lounging by them
on the sea, without seeking to cultivate a more intimate acquaintance, like some
poor devils ashore that happened to know an irrassable great man, they make
distant, unobtrusive salutations to him in the street, lest if they pursued the
acquaintance further, they might receive a summary thump for their presumption.
But not only did each of these famous whales enjoy great individual celebrity,
nay you may call it an oceanwide renown, not only was he famous in life and now
is immortal in the folks stories after death, but he was admitted into all the
rights, privileges, and distinctions of a name. Had as much a name indeed as
Cambisces or Caesar. Was it not so, oh Teour Tom, thou famed Leviathan, scarred
like an iceberg, whose so long dits lurk in the oriental straits of that name,
whose spout was often seen from the palmy beach of Bay? Was it not so, oh
New Zealand Jack, thou terror of all cruisers that cross their wakes in the
vicinity of the Tattoo Land? Was it not so, O Moran, king of Japan, whose lofty
jet, they say, at times assumed the semblance of a snow white cross against
the sky? Was it not so, oh Don Miguel, thou Chilean whale, marked like an old
tortoise with mystic hieroglyphics upon the back? In plain pros, here are four
whales as well known to the students of citation history as Marius or Cila to
the classic scholar.
But this is not all. New Zealand Tom and Don Miguel, after at various times
creating great havoc among the boats of different vessels, were finally gone in
quest of systematically hunted out, chased, and killed by valiant whailing
captains who heaved up their anchors with that express object as much in view
as in setting out through the Naraganset woods. Captain Butler of old had it in
his mind to capture that notorious murderous savage Anowan, the headmost
warrior of the Indian king Philillip.
I do not know where I can find a better place than just here to make mention of
one or two other things which seem to me important, as in printed form
establishing in all respects the reasonleness of the whole story of the
white whale, more especially the catastroph. For this is one of those
disheartening instances where truth requires full as much bolstering as
error. So ignorant are most landsmen of some of the plainest and most palpable
wonders of the world, that without some hints touching the plain facts,
historical and otherwise, of the fishery, they might scoff at Moby Dick
as a monstrous fable, or still worse and more detestable, a hideous and intolerable uh allegory.
First, though most men have some vague flitting ideas of the general perils of
the grand fishery, yet they have nothing like a fixed vivid conception of those
perils and the frequency with which they recur. One reason perhaps is that not
one in 50 of the actual disasters and deaths by casualties in the fishery ever
finds a public record at home, however transient and immediately forgotten that
record. Do you suppose that that poor fellow there who this moment perhaps
caught by the whale line off the coast of New Guinea is being carried to the
bottom of the sea by the sounding Leviathan? Do you suppose that that poor
fellow's name will appear in the newspaper obituary you will read
tomorrow at your breakfast? No, because the males are very irregular between
here and New Guinea. In fact, did you ever hear what might be called regular
news, direct or indirect, from New Guinea? Yet I tell you that upon one
particular voyage which I made to the Pacific, among many others, we spoke 30
different ships, every one of which had a death by a whale, some of them more
than one, and three that had each lost a boat's crew. For God's sake, be
economical with your lamps and candles.
Not a gallon you burn, but at least one drop of a man's blood was spilled for
it. Secondly, people assure have indeed some indefinite idea that a whale is an
enormous creature of enormous power, but I have ever found that when narrating to
them some specific example of this two-fold enormousness, they have
significantly complimented me upon my facitiousness. when I declare upon my
soul I had no more idea of being facicious than Moses when he wrote the
history of the plagues of Egypt. But fortunately the special point I hear
seek can be established upon testimony entirely independent of my own. The
point is this. The sperm whale is in some cases sufficiently powerful,
knowing, and judiciously malicious, as with direct a forethought to stave in,
utterly destroy, and sink a large ship.
And what is more, the sperm whale has done it. First, in the year 1820, the
ship Essex, Captain Pard of Nantucket, was cruising in the Pacific Ocean. One
day she saw spouts lowered her boats and gave chase to a shaw of sperm whales. He
long several of the whales were wounded when suddenly a very large whale
escaping from the boats issued from the shaw and bore directly down upon the
ship. Dashing his forehead against her hull, he so stove her in that in less
than quote 10 minutes end quote she settled down and fell over. Not a
surviving plank of her has been seen since. After the severest exposure, part
of the crew reached the land in their boats. Being returned home at last,
Captain Pard once more sailed for the Pacific in command of another ship. But
the gods shipwrecked him again upon unknown rocks and breakers. For the
second time his ship was utterly lost, and forth with forswearing the sea, he
has never tempted it since. At this day, Captain Pard is a resident of Nantucket.
I have seen Owen Chase, who was chief mate of the Essex at the time of the
tragedy. I have read his plain and faithful narrative. I have conversed
with his son, and all this within a few miles of the scene of the catastrophe.
Footnote. The following are extracts from Chase's narrative. Quote, "Every
fact seemed to warrant me in concluding that it was anything but chance which
directed his operations. He made two several attacks upon the ship at a short
interval between them, both of which, according to their direction, were
calculated to do us the most injury by being made ahead, and thereby combining
the speed of the two objects for the shock, to affect which, the exact
maneuvers which he made were necessary."
His aspect was most horrible, and such as indicated resentment and fury. He
came directly from the shaw which we had just before entered, and in which we had
struck three of his companions, as if fired with revenge for their sufferings.
End quote. again, quote, "At all events, the whole circumstances taken together,
all happening before my own eyes, and producing at the time impressions in my
mind of decided calculating mischief on the part of the whale, many of which
impressions I cannot now recall, induce me to be satisfied that I am correct in
my opinion." End quote. Here are his reflections sometime after quitting the
ship during a black night in an open boat when almost desparing of reaching
any hospitable shore. Quote, "The dark ocean and swelling waters were nothing.
The fears of being swallowed up by some dreadful tempest or dashed upon hidden
rocks with all the other ordinary subjects of fearful contemplation seemed
scarcely entitled to a moment's thought.
The dismal-looking wreck and the horrid aspect in revenge of the whale wholly
engrossed my reflections until day again made its appearance. End quote. In
another place, page 45, he speaks of the mysterious and mortal attack of the animal, end
of footnote.
Secondly, the ship Union also of Nantucket was in the year 1807 totally
lost off the Azors by a similar onset, but the authentic particulars of this
catastrophe I have never chance to encounter, though from the whale hunters
I have now and then heard casual illusions to it. Thirdly, some 18 or 20
years ago, Commodore J, then commanding an American sloop of war of the first
class, happened to be dining with a party of whailing captains on board a
Nantucket ship in the harbor of Aahu, Sandwich Islands. Conversation turning
upon whales, the commodor was pleased to be skeptical, touching the amazing
strength ascribed to them by the professional gentleman present. He
perempterly denied, for example, that any whale could so smite his stout sloop
of war as to cause her to leak so much as a thimbleful. "Very good, but there
is more coming." Some weeks after, the Commodore set sail in this impregnable
craft for Valparzo, but he was stopped on the way by a portly sperm whale that
begged a few moments confidential business with him. That business
consisted in fetching the Commodore's craft such a thack that with all his
pumps going, he made straight for the nearest port to heave down and repair. I
am not superstitious, but I consider the Commodore's interview with that whale as
providential. Was not Saul of Tarsus converted from unbelief by a similar
fright? I tell you, the sperm whale will stand no nonsense.
I will now refer you to Langdorf's voyages for a little circumstance in
point. Peculiarly interesting to the writer hereof. Langdorf, you must know,
by the way, was attached to the Russian Admiral Kruzen Stern's famous discovery
expedition in the beginning of the present century. Captain Langdor, thus
begins his 17th chapter. Quote, "By the 13th of May, our ship was ready to sail,
and the next day we were out in the open
sea on our way to Okoch. The weather was very clear and fine, but so intolerably
cold that we were obliged to keep on our fur clothing. For some days we had very
little wind. It was not till the 19th that a brisk gale from the Northwest
sprang up. An uncommon large whale, the body of which was larger than the ship
itself, lay almost at the surface of the water, but was not perceived by anyone
on board till the moment when the ship, which was in full sail, was almost upon
him, so that it was impossible to prevent its striking against him. We
were thus placed in the most imminent danger, as this gigantic creature,
setting up its back, raised the ship 3 ft at least out of the water. The mass
reeled and the sails fell altogether, while we who were below all sprang
instantly upon the deck, concluding that we had struck upon some rock. Instead of
this, we saw the monster sailing off with the utmost gravity and somnity.
Captain Dewolf applied immediately to the pumps to examine whether or not the
vessel had received any damage from the shock, but we found that very happily it
had escaped entirely uninjured. End quote. Now the captain to Wolf here
alluded to as commanding the ship in question is a New Englander who after a
long life of unusual adventures as a sea captain this day resides in the village
of Dorchester near Boston. I have the honor of being a nephew of his. I have
particularly questioned him concerning this passage in Langdor. He
substantiates every word. The ship, however, was by no means a large one, a
Russian craft built on the Siberian coast and purchased by my uncle after
bartering away the vessel in which he sailed from home.
In that up and down manly book of old-fashioned adventure, so full too of
honest wonders, the voyage of Lionel Wafer, one of ancient Dampier's old
chums, I found a little matter set down so like that just quoted from Langdorf,
that I cannot forbear inserting it here for a corroborative example, if such be
needed. Lionol, it seems, was on his way to John Ferdinando, as he calls the
modern Juan Fernandez.
Quote, in our way thither, he says, "About 4:00 in the morning, when we were
about 150 leagues from the Maine of America, our ship felt a terrible shock,
which put our men in such consternation that they could hardly tell where they
were or what to think. But everyone began to prepare for death. And indeed
the shock was so sudden and violent that we took it for granted the ship had
struck against a rock. But when the amazement was a little over, we cast the
lead and sounded, but found no ground.
The suddenness of the shock made the guns leap in their carriages, and
several of the men were shaken out of their hammocks. Captain Davis, who lay
with his head on a gun, was thrown out of his cabin. End quote. Lionel then
goes on to impute the shock to an earthquake and seems to substantiate the
imputation by stating that a great earthquake somewhere about that time did
actually do great mischief along the Spanish land. But I should not much
wonder if in the darkness of that early hour of the morning the shock was after
all caused by an unseen whale vertically bumping the hull from beneath.
I might proceed with several more examples, one way or another, known to
me of the great power and malice at times of the sperm whale. In more than
one instance, he has been known not only to chase the asailing boats back to
their ships, but to pursue the ship itself, and long withstand all the
lances hurled at him from its decks. The English ship Pusy Hall can tell a story
on that head. And as for his strength, let me say that there have been examples
where the lines attached to a running sperm whale have in a calm been
transferred to the ship and secured there, the whale towing her great hull
through the water as a horse walks off with a cart. Again, it is very often
observed that if the sperm whale, once struck, is allowed time to rally, then
he acts not so often with blind rage as with willful, deliberate designs of
destruction to his pursuers, nor is it without conveying some eloquent
indication of his character, that upon being attacked he will frequently open
his mouth and retain it in that dread expansion for several consecutive
minutes. But I must be content with only one more and a concluding illustration,
a remarkable and most significant one, by which you will not fail to see that
not only is the most marvelous event in this book corroborated by plain facts of
the present day, but that these marvels, like all marvels, are mere repetitions
of the ages, so that for the millionth time we say amen with Solomon, verily
there is nothing new under the sun.
In the sixth Christian century lived Precopius, a Christian magistrate of
Constantinople in the days when Justinian was emperor and Belliserius
general. As many know, he wrote the history of his own times, a work every
way of uncommon value. By the best authorities, he has always been
considered a most trustworthy and unexaggerating historian, except in some
one or two particulars, not at all affecting the matter presently to be
mentioned. Now in this history of his, Precopius mentions that during the term
of his prefixure at Constantinople, a great sea monster was captured in the
neighboring propontis or sea of Marmura after having destroyed vessels at
intervals in those waters for a period of more than 50 years. A fact thus set
down in substantial history cannot easily be gained, nor is there any
reason that it should be. of what precise species this sea monster was is
not mentioned, but as he destroyed ships as well as for other reasons, he must
have been a whale, and I am strongly inclined to think a sperm whale, and I
will tell you why. For a long time, I fancied that the sperm whale had been
always unknown in the Mediterranean and the deep waters connecting with it. Even
now I am certain that those seas are not and perhaps never can be in the present
constitution of things a place for his habitual gregarious resort. But further
investigations have recently proved to me that in modern times there have been
isolated instances of the presence of the sperm whale in the Mediterranean. I
am told on good authority that on the Barbar Coast a Commodore Davis of the
British Navy found the skeleton of a sperm whale. Now, as a vessel of war
readily passes through the dinels, hence a sperm whale could by the same route
pass out of the Mediterranean into the proponts.
In the propont, as far as I can learn, none of that peculiar substance called
Brit is to be found, the element of the right whale. But I have every reason to
believe that the food of the sperm whale, squid, or cuttlefish, lurks at
the bottom of that sea, because large creatures, but by no means the largest
of that sort, have been found at its surface. If then you properly put these
statements together and reason upon them a bit, you will clearly perceive that
according to all human reasoning, Precopius's sea monster that for half a
century stove the ships of a Roman emperor must in all probability have been a sperm whale.